<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://hl7.org/fhir ../../input-cache/schemas/R5/fhir-single.xsd">
  <a name="introduction"> </a>
  <h3>Introduction</h3>
  <p>This implementation guide contains common FHIR assets for use in US-based content IGs
    built using the approach and specifications developed as part of the Clinical
    Quality Framework (<a href="https://confluence.hl7.org/display/CQIWC/Clinical+Quality+Framework">CQF</a>)
    initiative, including the USCore-ModelInfo and USCommon libraries.</p>

  <a name="contents"> </a>
  <h3>Contents</h3>
  <p>This implementation guide contains libraries that facilitate the use of CQL with FHIR in the US Realm, 
  with an initial use case of Prior Authorization Support Questionnaires as described in the 
  <a href="https://hl7.org/fhir/us/davinci-dtr/">DaVinci Documentation Templates and Rules (DTR)</a> implementation guide.
  </p>

  <a name="pa-use-case"> </a>
  <h4>Prior Authorization Questionnaire Use Case</h4>
  <p>Links to resources for current prior authorization scenarios:</p>

  <ul>
    <li><a href="https://www.cms.gov/files/document/prior-authorization-and-pre-claim-review-program-statistics.pdf">Prior Authorization and Pre-Claim Review Program Stats (cms.gov)</a></li>
    <li><a href="https://www.cms.gov/data-research/monitoring-programs/medicare-fee-service-compliance-programs/prior-authorization-and-pre-claim-review-initiatives/prior-authorization-certain-hospital-outpatient-department-opd-services">Prior Authorization for Certain Hospital Outpatient Department (OPD) Services | CMS</a></li>
    <li><a href="https://provider.humana.com/coverage-claims/prior-authorizations/prior-authorization-lists">Preauthorization and Notification Lists for Healthcare Providers - Humana</a></li>
  </ul>

  <a name="patient"> </a>
  <h5>Patient</h5>
  <p>The following page provides patterns for accessing patient-level information in a questionnaire:</p>
  <a href="patterns-patient.html">Patient Patterns</a>

  <a name="usage"> </a>
  <h4>Usage</h4>
  <p>To use these libraries in your implementation guide, include a reference to this implementation guide as
    an implementation guide dependency:</p>
  <pre><code>&lt;dependsOn id=&quot;cqf-us&quot;&gt;
  &lt;uri value=&quot;http://fhir.org/guides/cqf/us/common/ImplementationGuide/fhir.cqf.us.common&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;packageId value=&quot;fhir.cqf.us.common&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;version value=&quot;0.1.0&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/dependsOn&gt;</code></pre>

  <a name="uscore-modelinfo"> </a>
  <h4>USCore ModelInfo</h4>
  <p>Clinical Quality Language (<a href="http://cql.hl7.org">CQL</a>) is a high-level,
  domain-specific language focused on clinical quality and targeted at measure and
  decision support artifact authors. In addition, the CQL specification provides a
  machine-readable canonical representation called Expression Logical Model
  (<a href="https://cql.hl7.org/04-logicalspecification.html">ELM</a>) targeted at
  implementations and designed to enable automated sharing of clinical knowledge.</p>
  <p>To use CQL with USCore, <a href="https://cql.hl7.org/07-physicalrepresentation.html#data-model-references">model
  information</a> must be provided to the implementation environment. The <a href="Library-USCore-ModelInfo.html">USCore-ModelInfo</a>
  library provides this information for US Core. To use USCore, include a <a href="https://cql.hl7.org/02-authorsguide.html#data-models">using
  declaration</a> as shown in the example below:</p>
  <pre><code>using USCore version '3.1.1'</code></pre>
  <p>Although not required by CQL, current best-practice is to include the version of USCore.</p>
</div>


